<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Uk-Higher-Ed on Max Long's Blog</title><link>https://maaxlong.github.io/blog/tags/uk-higher-ed/</link><description>Recent content in Uk-Higher-Ed on Max Long's Blog</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><managingEditor>your@email.com (Max Long)</managingEditor><webMaster>your@email.com (Max Long)</webMaster><lastBuildDate>Sun, 05 Oct 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://maaxlong.github.io/blog/tags/uk-higher-ed/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>GenAI at Oxford</title><link>https://maaxlong.github.io/blog/posts/genai-at-oxford/</link><pubDate>Sun, 05 Oct 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>your@email.com (Max Long)</author><guid>https://maaxlong.github.io/blog/posts/genai-at-oxford/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;The University of Oxford have recently published new guidance on the use of &lt;a href="https://www.ox.ac.uk/research/support-researchers/research-practice/policy-generative-ai-research"&gt;Generative AI in Research&lt;/a&gt;, as well as new policies on the use of &lt;a href="https://academic.admin.ox.ac.uk/ai-use-in-summative-assessment"&gt;GenAI in summative assessments&lt;/a&gt;. The university has also published guidance on the &lt;a href="https://www.ox.ac.uk/students/life/it/guidance-safe-and-responsible-use-gen-ai-tools"&gt;safe and responsible use of GenAI tools&lt;/a&gt;. This follows a &lt;a href="https://www.ox.ac.uk/news/2025-09-19-oxford-becomes-first-uk-university-offer-chatgpt-edu-all-staff-and-students"&gt;recent deal between the University and OpenAI&lt;/a&gt;, which will see ChatGPT Edu made available to all users in the university.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Much of this is very informative, and it feels like a positive step to have clearly articulated policies on the use of GenAI in a university context, especially one which lays out guidance for both students and researchers. However, as with any blanket set of policies and recommendations, there still remain questions as to how these will apply within the context of individual subjects and fields, and how the use of specific tools and methods should be reported, registered, and cited. This is particularly the case in many fields, including History, where registering the declaring the use of specific tools and data associated has not been common practice in the past, except in the case of digital humanities specialists.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title/><link>https://maaxlong.github.io/blog/posts/another-post/</link><pubDate>Wed, 01 Oct 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>your@email.com (Max Long)</author><guid>https://maaxlong.github.io/blog/posts/another-post/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;This weekend we celebrated the career of Prof. Peter Mandler with a book launch and a conference featuring contributions from friends and colleagues across his career. The book, entitled Democratising History: Modern British History Inside and Out, is edited by Freddy Foks, Laura Carter, and Philip Harling. The introduction, by Laura and Freddy, is a particularly rich contribution to the field, outlining a rough genealogy for the concept of ‘democratisation’, which has so far received surprisingly little detailed attention by historians of Britain. The book is &lt;a href="https://uolpress.co.uk/book/democratising-history/"&gt;available to download&lt;/a&gt; for free now!&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>